Guide to the Friends of Duke Chapel Records, 1973 - 1999 UA.17.03.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Friends of Duke Chapel records
1973 - 1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Friends of Duke Chapel
UA.17.03.0001
1.5 Linear Feet
The Friends of Duke Chapel was founded in 1974 to provide the means for interested persons to organize into an ongoing, supportive, participatory group to support the ministry and program of Duke Chapel. The records consist of correspondence, official letters to members, advisory board and committee minutes and reports, newsletters, and other organization publications. Materials are present from 1973 to 1999. English.
1000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
No restrictions.
Provenance
The Friends of Duke Chapel Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1979-1994.
Historical Note
The Friends of Duke Chapel was founded in 1974 to provide the means for interested persons to organize into an ongoing, supportive, participatory group to support the ministry and program of Duke Chapel. The Friends open membership to anyone interested in the Chapel and its program. It grew out of a predecessor group called the Full Membership Chapel Group, organized under and continuing the name of Duke University Church (Interdenominational). Full Members supported the Chapel program but membership was limited to persons affiliated with the University either as faculty or staff. As part of its mission, the Friends of Duke Chapel provide funds to aid numerous aspects of the Chapel program such as the chapel choir, organ, vestments, renovation needs, and provision of televised services. Membership benefits included weekly mailing of the Sunday bulletin, announcements and invitations to services, concerts, and music programs, as well as a Friends of Duke Chapel newsletter.
The Friends have continuously helped fund and contribute to numerous initiatives and renovations of the Chapel, including the construction of a handicapped ramp access to the Chapel, installation of the Flentrop organ, and providing televised access to the Sunday services for patients at Duke Medical Center. They also contributed to enriching the preaching and theologian-in-residence programs.
An Advisory Board governs the group. Originally a nine-person board, it was enlarged to a thirteen person board in 1981, always including the Dean of the Chapel. Past board members include William Stokes, Helen Crotwell, Jack Blackburn, Arthur Kale, William King, Ella Jean Shore, Carolyn Penny, and Mary Parkerson, who became the first Friends Director in 1980.
Collection Overview
These records were produced by the Friends of Duke Chapel in the course of their activities as a support organization for the program of Duke Chapel. Materials are present from 1973 to 1999. The bulk of the records consists of correspondence, official letters to members, advisory board and committee minutes and reports, newsletters, and other organization publications. There is some material not directly produced by the Friends of Duke Chapel but mentions the organization in its publications, or deals with the history of Duke Chapel.
Related Material
Duke University Church records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Duke Memorial records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Chapel Sermons [Sound Recordings].
University Archives, Duke University.
Church fund raising; Chapels -- North Carolina -- Durham; Friends of Duke Chapel; Friends of Duke Chapel; Duke University. Chapel; Duke University -- Religious activities; Duke University -- Buildings
- Minutes and Reports, 1975-1991
  Scope and Contents note
  This series chronicles the interests and activities of the Friends of Duke Chapel from 1975 to 1991. It includes minutes and agendas from advisory board meetings, annual meeting minutes, as well as reports from the finance and nominating committees. The advisory board minutes changed name from "Executive Committee Minutes" to "Advisory Board Minutes" in 1981. Some topics covered in the minutes include construction of a handicapped ramp, meetings with guest preachers, brochure on Memorial Chapel, creation of a directorship for Friends of Duke Chapel, air-conditioning of the Chapel, annual Messiah luncheon, photographing of Chapel windows, Advent and Lenten prayer booklets, Chapel window bookmark project, and establishment of a Friends of the Chapel endowment fund.
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1976-1981 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Board Minutes and Agendas, 1981-1991 (Box 1)
  - Annual Meeting Minutes, 1978-1990 (Box 1)
  - Finance Committee Reports and Budgets, 1977-1988 (Box 1)
  - Nominating Committee Reports, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1973-1999
  This series contains correspondence relating to the activities and administration of the Friends of Duke Chapel. It includes general correspondence from members of the advisory board to other board members and members at large. These letters include those from Dean of the Chapel Robert T. Young regarding the proposal and implementation of the Friends group in 1973. There is also a folder containing official letters from the Director to the membership at large regarding upcoming events such as Messiah performances, membership renewals, and annual meetings.
  - Correspondence, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1987 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Letters to Members, 1974-1999 (Box 1)
- Subject Files, 1973-1989
  This series includes material relating to the function of the Friends of Duke Chapel. It is arranged alphabetically. Material includes by-laws and resolutions, a description and background statement regarding the mission of the Friends group, membership lists, and news clippings relating to the history of Duke Chapel. In addition, there are records from the organizing committee relating to the founding of the group and the definition of its mission. Of particular interest in this series are the oral history transcriptions of interviews conducted by Arthur Kale of Barney L. Jones, James T. Cleland, Howard Wilkinson, and Robert DuBose. The transcriptions are a rich source of historical information on the staff and history of the Chapel and its program. The interviews provide personal reminiscences of chapel history and staff, including Foster Barnes, Mildred Hendrix, Frank Hickman, Ben Smith, and the carillonneurs. They discuss their relationships with numerous campus organizations, athletics, the inter-racial council, and the role of the administrative committee. The men remember visits and sermons by guest preachers such as Ralph Sockman, Martin Niemoller, Henry Crane, and Paul Tillich. They also recall chapel events throughout the calendar year including Religious Emphasis week, the Christmas pageant, and Easter services.
  Other significant materials are several speeches, by Bishop W. Kenneth Goodson, Mary D. B. T. Semans, and Marjorie C. Jones respectively, given during the Friends annual dinner meeting. Bishop Goodson, former Bishop-in-Residence of the Divinity School and trustee emeritus of the Duke Endowment, fondly remembers his relationship to Duke Chapel. Mary D. B. T. Semans speech recalls her mother Sarah P. Duke's feelings for the Chapel, and includes her memories of numerous Chapel ministers and music staff. Marjorie Jones gives insight into the role of chapel hostesses and the life of the chapel during the week. [See also: Barney L. Jones Papers for "Chapel Reminiscences: The First Two Decades," a speech given to the Friends of Duke Chapel Annual Dinner, 1983.]
  - Advisory Board, 1984-1991 (Box 1)
  - Annual Meeting, Speech by Bishop W. Kenneth Goodson, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Annual Meeting, Speech by Mary D. B. T. Semans, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Annual Meeting, Speech by Marjorie C. Jones, 1983 (Box 1)
  - By-Laws and Resolutions, 1975-1981 (Box 1)
  - Description and Background Statement, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Development Committee, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Full Membership Chapel Group, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1975-1989 (Box 1)
  - Nominating Committee, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Oral history transcriptions of interviews with Barney Jones, James T. Cleland, Howard Wilkinson, and Robert DuBose, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Organizing Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
- Publications, 1975-1999
  This series includes brochures and pamphlets relating to the Chapel and work of the Friends group and calendars produced by the Friends. Brochures include the Friends informational and membership brochures, and a bookmark featuring the Adam Window-South Aisle of the Chapel.
  - Brochures and other Publications, 1978-1997 (Box 1)
  - Calendar, 2009-2010 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Calendar, 2010-2011 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Calendar, 2011-2012 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Calendar, 2012-2013 (Oversize-folder 1)